So בוקר טוב. boker tov.
So today's דף daf is ד'. dalet.
We pick up at the bottom of ג' עמוד ב'. Gimmel Amud
Bet. And we are discussing this issue of this ברייתא brayta that
talks about the status of the egg. And
one of the things that the ברייתא brayta said was that if
there's a doubt, it's forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says this is
a real challenge according to those that understand the problem of the
egg is a rabbinic problem about like fruit from a tree or
liquids that flow. You can add מוקצה. muktzeh.
And the גמרא Gemara says well maybe we're talking in the end
of it about a case of a טרפה trefah issue. But then
we have a problem about the other הלכה halakha in the משנה
mishna that says that if it's mixed up with a thousand they're
all forbidden. So if it's the problem of יום טוב yom tov
related then you understand it's a principle of דבר שיש לו מתירין,
dabar she'yesh lo mattirin, don't eat it now wait till tomorrow. But
if it's a problem of טרפה trefah why would it be that
it would be forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says well maybe the
idea is that the egg is a significant object it's like it,
you know, it has some independent identity and therefore does not become
part of a conglomerate and that's the question of
דבר שבמנין, dabar she'be'minyan, something that would normally be counted. גמרא Gemara
says that only works if your category is כל שדרכו למנות, kol
she'darko limnot, things that are sometimes done by counting and other times
another means volume or weight or a basket of eggs. But if
you say that the only thing that is not בטל battel is
את שדרכו למנות, et she'darko limnot, things that are only sold by
number, then an egg should be בטל. battel. So we're back to
our question. Why is the egg not בטל battel if we're dealing
with a case of a טרפה. trefah. Again, יום טוב yom tov
case then wait till tomorrow, we understand why it's not בטל, battel,
but if it's a טרפה, trefah, why is the egg not בטל
battel if it gets mixed up. So we pick up with that
and the גמרא Gemara says the following.
So five lines from the bottom, last word on the line, אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, line beginning with the word Pappa. So
says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, האי תנא תנא דליטרא קציעות הוא. hai
tanna tanna de'litra ketzi'ot hu.
The author of this ברייתא brayta that says that the egg is
not בטל battel is the
author of the ברייתא brayta of the ליטרא, litra, like a liter,
of קציעות, ketzi'ot, which are cakes of figs
or dates, they always get them mixed up,
of figs. So what is that, of the משנה. mishna. So what
is that, it's משנה mishna ברייתא brayta this question here because it
is a משנה mishna but it's expanded in the ברייתא. brayta. דאמר
De'amar and anyway we will see that this משנה mishna ברייתא brayta
says כל דבר שבמנין אפילו דרבנן לא בטל. kol dabar she'be'minyan afilu
de'rabbanan lo battel.
We're still going to stick to our guns and say the reason
the egg is not בטל battel is because it is something that
is counted. Now, but you pointed out to me that it's possible
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who focuses on things that are counted
would only talk about things that are only counted and an egg
is not only counted. Not a problem. I'm going to show you
an author of a תנא tanna that holds that even things that
are sometimes counted are not בטל. battel. Not only that, even if
the thing is only a דרבנן de'rabbanan problem as long as it's
sometimes counted it is not בטל. battel. What is that, let's take
a look. וכל שכן דאורייתא Ve'kol sheken de'orayta and certainly in the
biblical problem like we're trying to say the case of the egg
is a טרפה trefah issue. דתנן De'nan we taught in a משנה,
mishna, I said it's also a ברייתא brayta because the ברייתא brayta
is the expanded version and we have the expanded version here. ליטרא
קציעות, Litra ketzi'ot, if you have a ליטרא litra or a container,
a barrel of these pressed figs and basically they would press figs
into cakes and they would turn it into like a huge big,
like it would basically be like you'd have these rounds, I think
that's how they used to make cheese, right? Anyway, you know, basically
if you have your barrel, right, anybody ever see you can have
like these round you'd have these like rounds of, you know, you'd
have these like you press these things into the barrel, these rounds
of figs. This would be a round of all these pressed figs
together, right? And you'd have them all sort of stacked in a
barrel and then you'd chop off sections and you would sell them.
So you have this ליטרא קציעות, litra ketzi'ot, you have these this
barrel full of these pressed figs.
שדרסה על פי עיגול, She'darsa al pi igul, that you pressed it
in this עיגול, igul, the עיגול igul is the barrel. Okay. So
here was your ליטרא קציעות, litra ketzi'ot, your
now that I'm standing I'm going to wind up using the board
more which is I guess a good thing. Here is your sort
of your round of pressed figs and
your quantity of pressed figs, your ליטרא, litra, and you pressed them
into the barrel. Now what's the issue? The issue the problem is
that these figs are תרומה terumah and you pressed them in the
barrel and you don't want to have to keep everything of תרומה.
terumah. So let's take a look.
So
ואיני יודע באיזה עיגול דרסה, ve'eni yodea be'eizeh igul darsa, you don't
know in which עיגול igul you
pressed them, על פי חבית al pi khavit ואיני יודע באיזה חבית
דרסה, ve'eni yodea be'eizeh khavit darsa, I'm sorry, I read the almost
wrong משנה. mishna. ואיני יודע באיזה עיגול דרסה, ve'eni yodea be'eizeh igul
darsa, that's one case, that you pressed them in an עיגול igul
in a barrel. In a container and you don't know which container.
Or על פי חבית al pi chavit in a barrel, ואיני יודע
באיזה חבית דרסת. ve'eini yode'a be'izeh chavit darasta. You don't know which
barrel you pressed them in. על פי כוורת al pi kiveret which
is another type of barrel, literally it means a beehive, but it
was a type of a cylindrical container, ואיני יודע באיזה כוורת דרסת.
ve'eini yode'a be'izeh kiveret darasta. Okay? So it's all three scenarios, but
it's the same point. You have a quantity, a ליטרא, litra, and
again, the fact that it was using this idea of a liter
or whatever a quantity is significant because it shows that these are
not things that are sold by counting. These are things that could
be sold by volume, by weight, etc. Okay, so that's going to
be important, that they're often not sold by counting. And you pressed
this quantity of things into a barrel. But you have dozens of
barrels and you forgot which one. And guess what? That quantity of
things, those figs, are all תרומה. terumah. And now, the basic הלכה
halacha is that תרומה, terumah, you need a hundred to cause ביטול
bitul by תרומה, terumah, okay? A hundred times as much. So basically,
imagine that I've got, right, a lot of barrels here. All of
them have pressed figs. Okay. This quantity in this one is one
ליטרא. litra. Okay, one ליטרא litra is the quantity of the תרומה
terumah that I pressed. How much would you need to say, and
I don't know which one it's in, that there is ביטול? bitul?
So, you could say, well, count up all the quantity of figs
here, all the quantity of figs in all the barrels, and if
there's a hundred ליטראס, litras, it's בטל, batel, right? But that's really
not fair. Why is that not fair? Because you know that your
figs are at the top of one of the barrels. Right? It's
not like they're somewhere in here. You did על פי חבית, al
pi chavit, right? על פי עיגול. al pi igul. You did it
at the top. So logically what you would need is the only
תערובת, ta'arovet, the only things that are in the doubt, are the
tops of all these barrels. So what you would need logically is
a hundred barrels. Okay? So let's see what the משנה mishna says
you need in order to get ביטול. bitul. Okay?
So...
But what if she had a hundred times volume? Two barrels?
Oh, a hundred times the vol... meaning the volume of a hundred
times.
Yeah, just take the tops. Right.
So that's an interesting possibility. The thing is, can you do that?
Are you looking at the top as an independent unit? Like, if
you have one apple that's ערלה orlah mixed up in like other
apples that are ערלה, orlah, do you look at how much, you
know, what's the total volume of those apples or do you count
how many apples you have? It could be that when you're not
dealing with something like a stew and a soup that gets all
equally distributed, but you're dealing with independent units, you need 60 times
the units or 100 times units, you know, because in the end,
the question is which of these units, it's not like a total
or so a volume of volume.
Does that not make sense? Well, okay.
You understand the difference?
If you drop a drop into soup, then the question is it
disperses equally, and then it's a question of proportional volume, is there
enough for ביטול bitul to a certain degree of dispersion. If you
have an issue of independent units, and we say you need 60
other units or 100 other units, 60 other or 100 other, 60
other or 100 other units, not volume.
But we said here we're not looking at this as units.
Oh, no, we're right to look at the top of the barrel
as the unit.
So we're looking at it as volume.
Well, yes, we did describe that this is a volume,
but now that we're trying to deal with ביטול, bitul, then we
don't know, is it
this top of this barrel, the top of this, the top of
this? And that's really a question of which unit is it. So
let's take a look at what it says.
Okay, רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
that this is a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי
יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. And here's his version of the debate. רבי מאיר
אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, so רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said the
following: רואין את העליונות כאילו הן פרודות, ro'in et ha'elyonot ke'ilu hen
perudot, you see the tops of the barrels as if they're separate,
והתחתונות מעלות את העליונות, vehatachtonot ma'alot et ha'elyonot, the bottoms of the
barrels can מעלות, ma'alot, meaning create ביטול bitul with the top. Which
means you don't look at it as if each top is the
thing that you're in doubt of. You look at it as if
you don't treat the top, you know, as if you know distinctly
where it is. It's separate, it's mixed in with everything else. And
therefore you can look at a hundred which includes the bottoms of
the barrels. And a hundred times, maybe it is the volume and
the quantity and so on. Okay, so he says technically you're right,
your only question is the tops of the barrels, but I'm going
to go easy on you. Now, part of the reason we can
go easy on you is very often you have these things, particularly
by תרומה דרבנן, terumah derabbanan, by תרומה terumah which is like rabbinic
תרומה, terumah, rabbinic תרומה terumah because it's fruit. Biblical תרומה terumah only
applies by דגן תירוש ויצהר, dagan tirosh veyitzhar, which
is
wine, oil, and grain. Okay, so but the תרומה terumah of fruit
is only rabbinic. And sometimes we find that the Rabbis were lenient
about the תרומה terumah of fruit. For example, I'll give you a
more radical case, which is, I don't know if it's more radical.
But you have two boxes of תרומה *Trumah* and one box of
תרומה *Trumah* and one box of חולין *Chullin*. And below you have
two big vats, one of תרומה *Trumah* and one of חולין *Chullin*.
And one box, you know, box one fell into vat A and
box two fell into vat B, and you don't know did the
תרומה *Trumah* fall into the תרומה *Trumah* or the תרומה *Trumah* fall
into the חולין *Chullin*. The משנה mishna *Mishnah* says well, you assume
the תרומה *Trumah* fell into the תרומה *Trumah*. Why do I assume
that? Right? So again, because that case was a case of rabbinic
תרומה *Trumah*, they went easy on you. So it's an interesting idea.
They're not just saying you don't need to satisfy the requirement. Yes,
you need to satisfy the requirement, but sometimes we'll go easy in
interpreting what it means to satisfy the requirement. You understand the difference?
Like, forget about this, but you need this, but here we'll consider
the hundred to be not a hundred tops of the barrels, but
it includes the bottoms of the barrels as well. Okay, that's what
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says. רואין את היונקות כאילו הן
פרודות *Ro'in et hayenokot ke'illu hen perudot*. You see the tops of
the barrels like they're distinct, but distinct here actually means distinct and
mixed in. התחתונות מעלות את העליונות *Hatachtonot ma'alot et ha'elyonot*. You can
use the bottoms to raise up, to cause ביטול bitul *Bitul*, and
you consider the entire, you know, it's mixed in with all of
the quantity of all of the barrels, not just the top. רבי
יהושע אומר *Rabbi Yehoshua omer*, רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says the more
straightforward thing. אם יש מאה פומים יעלו *Im yesh me'ah pumim ya'alu*.
If there are a hundred mouths of barrels, then it's בטל batel?
*Batel* because the question is about the tops of the barrels. ואם
לאו הפומים אסורים *Ve'im lav hapumim asurim*,
the tops of the barrels of all the barrels are forbidden because
you don't know which one is תרומה *Trumah*. והשוליים מותרים *Vehashulayim mutarim*,
and the bottoms are permitted. So רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says the
straight approach. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer. *Rabbi Eliezer* is more lenient, allows
creative interpretation of where the stuff is to create ביטול bitul *Bitul*.
That's רבי מאיר'ס *Rabbi Meir's* version of the debate. רבי יהודה אומר
*Rabbi Yehuda omer*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says no, here's the debate.
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer* says אם יש שם מאה פומים יעלו ואם לאו הפומים
אסורים והשוליים מותרים *Im yesh sham me'ah pumim ya'alu ve'im lav hapumim
asurim vehashulayim mutarim*. That רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* does not
start with his creative leniency. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* starts
more strict. He says that you go by a hundred tops of
barrels. If there are a hundred other barrels, then it's בטל batel,
*Batel*. If not, not because you could only look at the top
of the barrel. ורבי יהושע *VeRabbi Yehoshua*, not only so see you
see רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*, everybody is one level more
stringent than the previous version. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
already starts more stringent and says you go by the tops of
barrels. So how will רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* be more stringent? I
mean, the tops of the barrels should certainly be enough. So רבי
יהושע אומר *Rabbi Yehoshua omer* no, אפילו יש שם שלוש מאות פומים
לא יעלו *Afilu yesh sham shelosh me'ot pumim lo ya'alu*. Even if
there are three hundred tops of barrels there, it will not be
בטל batel *Batel*. Okay, now, and let's read the end and then
go back and unpack that, but that's obviously a very radical statement.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דרסה בעיגול ואינו יודע באיזה עיגול
דרסה *Darsa be'igul ve'eino yode'a be'eizeh igul darsa*. Now if it is
in the,
if you pressed it in the top of a barrel, an עיגול
*Igul* is a type of a container, and you don't know which
one, דברי הכל יעלו *Divrei hakol ya'alu*. Then everybody would agree it's
בטל batel *Batel*. הא דברי הכל ואי פלגי *Ha divrei hakol ve'ai
palgei*. Everybody would agree it's בטל batel *Batel*. This is exactly the
point we've been debating, that it's at the top of the barrel
and you don't know which barrel it's in. No, אמר רב פפא
Rav Pappa. הכי קאמר *Amar Rav Pappa hachi ka'amar*. This is what
the end of that ברייתא braita *Baraita* means. דרסה בעיגול ואינו יודע
באיזה מקום עיגול דרסה *Darsa be'igul ve'eino yode'a be'eizeh makom igul darsa*.
You pressed it in a barrel, but you don't know where it
is in the barrel. אם לצפונה אם לדרומה *Im litzfona im ledaroma*,
the north, the top of the barrel, the bottom, the middle of
the barrel. Then דברי הכל יעלו *Divrei hakol ya'alu*. That's easy because
then it's not just the question is which top of the barrel
is תרומה *Trumah*. It's where is the תרומה *Trumah* in all of
these figs, right? Because you don't know top, middle, which barrel. So
then everybody says ביטול bitul *Bitul* works. But if it's at the
top, then there is this debate. Now the question is the issue
is here you have, according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, you have
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* saying it's not בטל batel *Batel*. And remember
this is even rabbinic. This is the תרומה *Trumah* of figs. It's
not grain, it's not wine, it's not oil. This is rabbinic. And
even so, he says it's not בטל *Batel*. Why is it not
בטל *Batel*? It's not בטל *Batel* because here he is of the
opinion anything that is counted, even sometimes counted, is never בטל *Batel*
even if it's only a rabbinic problem. So he says these circles,
you sometimes sell them by weight, you sometimes sell them like by
volume, a whole barrel full of them, but sometimes you sell them
by unit. I'm going to sell you one circle, one round of
pressed figs. So since it is sometimes sold by unit, he says
it's not בטל *Batel*. So again, this is a long answer to
the question why is the egg mixed up with other eggs not
בטל *Batel*. If it's the simple reason that it's a יום טוב
Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* problem, so fine, wait till tomorrow. דבר שיש
לו מתירין davar sheyesh lo matirin. *Davar sheyesh lo matirin*. But in
order to get out of this question of, you know, oh that
if it you know it might be it's another issue and how
then will we explain that you know you know why it's not
בטל *Batel*. It might, so then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had to
say that
it's a because in order to address the other issue about the
issue of ספק safek *Safek*. Right? There were two things to
remind us, right? There were two things that were in the משנה
Mishna *Mishnah* that said, I'm really don't know why I keep doing
this more than a lot. What does it say?
ספק אסורות safek assurot?
*Safek asurot* ונתערבו באלף *Venitarvu be'elef*. כולם אסורים. So here is the
גמרא’s Gemara problem. Why is ספק safek אסורות? So if it’s Rabbinic,
you should say a ספק safek. Rabbinic is lenient. So it says,
okay, this is talking about a special case of טרפה. treifa. But
if it's a case, but how do you explain this line, that
even in the mixture they’re all אסור? assur? If it was the
Rabbinic problem of יום טוב, Yom Tov we understand. This is the
idea of
דבר שיש לו מתירין. davar sheyesh lo matirin? But if it’s you
created the space of טרפה, treifa, why should it not be בטל?
And that’s why we introduced all of this to say, because there’s
an opinion out there that anything that is sometimes counted, like these
figs and like an egg, even if it’s not always counted, will
never be בטל, even if it’s only a Rabbinic problem. Okay, so
we’ve managed to successfully say that this line is talking about טרפה,
treifa, and the reason it’s not בטל is because eggs are sometimes
counted. But it’s a very דחוק dachuk read of that ברייתא braita
to introduce טרפה, treifa, and then introduce this idea that even something
like an egg, which is often sold in other ways, because it’s
sometimes sold in units, is not counted.
Can I just say דבר שיש לו מתירין? davar sheyesh lo matirin
Could you rearticulate conceptually
דבר
שבמנין, davar shebimyan, why should ביטול bitul not apply?
Yeah, because it’s like if I have, it’s like a וואָרט vort
I have about when you talk about why we don’t count people,
right, and the beginning of, you know,
כי תשא. Ki Tisa. So it’s because people should never be things
that can just be amalgamated. Every person, right, is unique. So you
don’t just say, you don’t just say, oh I’ve got a group
of ten people here. You know, no, you know, you know, I’ve
got Joe and I’ve got Michael and I’ve got Charlie and I’ve
got Joe. You can’t just say, oh you know, it’s ten generic
people and they all combine together to be a group, right? So
if that, that's the same idea of
דבר שבמנין, davar shebimyan, right? You, each, if these things are only
sold by number, then that means that each one is independently significant.
ביטול bittul, works by
saying it’s all part of a conglomerate, of an amalgamated group, and
it loses its identity. Individual gets lost. But some things refuse to
become part of a group. You know, everything is an individualist, if
you think about it. So it’s דבר שבמנין, davar shebimyan, every single
egg is an individualist and it refuses to be, it refuses to
be part of a group. And since it refuses to be part
of a group, there’s no way we can consider the idea of
ביטול bitul itself. Okay, so let’s continue. Alright? So that’s one explanation.
One explanation is that the reason ספק safek is a problem, even
though it’s only Rabbinic, is because it’s טרפה. treifa. How do you
explain this? It’s a יום טוב Yom Tov issue and a דרבנן
d'rabbanan issue, you have to wait. But if it was a טרפה,
treifa, how do you explain this? And the idea centrally is דבר
שבמנין. davar shebimyan. Now let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
פפא הכי קאמר. Amar Papa hachi qamar. I'm sorry, I just did
that. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, Rav Ashi says, לעולם ספק
יום טוב ספק חול, le’olam safek Yom Tov safek chol, לעולם ספק
יום טוב ספק חול. le’olam safek Yom Tov safek chol. Okay, yes,
we’re going to go back. The issue is not an issue of
a טרפה. treifa. The issue is this egg is a מוקצה muktzah
problem. It’s the problem of, you know, the juices that run off,
or the juices that run off, or the fruit that falls off.
It’s all a Rabbinic problem. It’s all a Rabbinic problem, great. We
understand why it’s not בטל because of wait until tomorrow. But then
we have to go back to this issue of ספק. safek If
it’s a doubt whether it was born on יום טוב Yom Tov,
or on חול, chol, then it’s a Rabbinic ספק safek, and we
should be lenient. So why, so if we’re going to read the
ברייתא braita. simply like, you know, without introducing the idea of טרפה,
treifa, and it’s a question of a Rabbinic issue of using it
on יום טוב, Yom Tov why should a ספק safek be a
problem? So let’s see what he says. רב אשי אמר לעולם ספק
יום טוב ספק חול. Rav Ashi amar le’olam safek Yom Tov safek
chol. But here’s why it’s going to be forbidden: הוי דבר שיש
לו מתירין, havei davar sheyesh lo matirin, because דבר שיש לו מתירין
davar sheyesh lo matirin אפילו בדרבנן לא בטיל. afilu b’d’rabbanan lo batil.
The same reason you can accept that the egg on יום טוב
Yom Tov, is not כשר kasher because the idea is wait until
tomorrow, and anything that’s במנין bimyan לא בטיל. lo batil. That’s the
same reason why you should say that a ספק, safek a doubt,
should be forbidden. Although we normally say a doubt in a דרבנן
d'rabbanan is permissible, here it’s a doubt in a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, but
the point is the same: wait until tomorrow. Okay, if the principle
behind the reason the egg is not בטל when it gets mixed
up is because you might as well just wait until tomorrow, we’re
not going to let ביטול work, well, that answers your question of
why a ספק safek, is also forbidden. It’s true it’s only a
Rabbinic problem, but why use this rule of ספק דרבנן לקולא safek
d'rabbanan l'kula if you can just wait until tomorrow? Okay, now that
is a big חידוש, chiddush, because normally the idea of דבר שיש
לו מתירין davar she-yesh lo matirin was only said by this idea
of a mixture, right? It’s not said by this general issue of
being lenient in a case of doubts by דרבנן. d'rabbanan. We, you
know,
that is not at all the standard usage of it. And imagine
the halakhic implications of that idea, right? So you could even abstract
it further, and some people do this, so even when they’re dealing
with a שאלה shaila which is on a דרבנן d'rabbanan matter and
there’s... even to be lenient they'll say yeah, but you know what,
better play it safe. That's just to be strict anyway, right? Which
is what this is sort of saying: better just wait till tomorrow,
don't rely on this idea that a ספק of a דרבנן. derabbanan.
So if you abstract it more, right, it could be used, but
even if you don't abstract it more it has profound implications. So
for example the whole issue that came out throughout the Middle Ages
of eating חדש, chadash, of eating grain that you don't know whether
it was before the עומר omer or after, right? Before the second
day of פסח Pesach or after? So one of the whole arguments
was, well, we can allow it, and this is the what became
the primary argument, that even if you say it's דאורייתא de-Oraita we
can allow because of a double doubt, a ספק ספיקא. sfek sfeka.
But what's the double doubt? Maybe it grew this year, maybe it
grew last year because they had a lot of old grain in
storage. Even if it was this year's grain, maybe it was grain
that took root before the עומר. omer. So, which is funny because
it's all boils down to one question: is it ישן yashan or
is it חדש? chadash? But they constructed it as a double doubt.
And then the question is, but wait a minute, guess what חדש
chadash is? חדש chadash is דבר שיש לו
מתירים.
davar she-yesh
lo matirin. It will become permissible after the second day of
פסח. Pesach. So,
if you say דבר שיש לו מתירים davar she-yesh lo matirin is
not only a rule by ביטול, but is even a rule in
the principles of being lenient in a cases of doubt, so who
cares about your ספק ספיקא? sfek sfeka? It's a דבר שיש לו
מתירים. davar she-yesh lo matirin. Wait until next year. So, maybe there's
a difference between a ספק ספיקא sfek sfeka and a ספק דרבנן,
safek derabbanan, but this idea is a very nice read of the
ברייתא. braita It's all talking about the egg, it's all talking about
יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's not בטל because wait till tomorrow. The
whole question was, okay, but it's forbidden to be lenient in the
case of a ספק, and the answer is, since you can wait
until tomorrow, דבר שיש לו מתירים, davar she-yesh lo matirin, then we
can't even apply the principle of a ספק דרבנן לקולא. safek derabbanan
lekulla. Which as I said has really profound implications saying that even
this idea you say just wait until tomorrow, wait until it becomes
permissible. Yes.
A child, a baby boy who is born either late Friday afternoon
or early Friday night and we aren't sure, we do the ברית,
bris, we wait till Sunday for the ברית.
bris. Yeah, correct.
So this is another but
that's just the principle of ספק דאורייתא לחומרא. safek de-Oraita lehumra. You
don't want to violate שבת Shabbos potentially.
Ah, okay, but it's not דרבנן.
derabbanan. Okay, so that's his read of the ברייתא braita which is
a much easier read but with pretty significant implications. Now we're going
to go on to another ברייתא braita. about the egg, and this
is a תוספתא. Tosefta. תניא, Tanya, we find in a
ברייתא. Braisa. אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, others say, meaning רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir משום רבי אליעזר, mishum Rebbi Eliezer, so here again is a
tradition רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, had in the name of רבי אליעזר.
ביצה תאכל, Beitzah techal, היא ואמה. hi ve-imma. The egg can be
eaten,
he or תאכל tochal you should eat it, anyway, he and its
mother. So go ahead, eat the egg, eat the hen, not a
problem. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan,
what type of scenario are we talking about? אילימא בתרנגולת העומדת לאכילה,
Ilima betarnegolet ha-omedet la-achilah, if it's a hen that's set aside for
eating, right, that's been our question all along, so then basically what
he's saying is the hen isn't מוקצה muktzah because it's set aside
for eating, it's ייחדה yichdah for eating remember, and the egg he's
saying like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, it's also not a problem, whatever
problem you come up with like fruit that drop off from a
tree, that's not an issue. Go ahead, eat the egg, eat the
mother. So the גמרא Gemara says, if that's true, פשיטא, pshita, דהיא
ואמה שריא, de-hi ve-imma sharya, that's obvious, then obviously the egg is
permissible, but as רש״י Rashi says, it's obvious the mother is permissible.
Why do you have to tell me the mother is permissible? Nobody
ever debates the mother if it's a hen sitting around to be
turned into food. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא בתרנגולת העומדת לגדל
ביצים. Ella betarnegolet ha-omedet legadel beitzim. So let's say it's talking about
a hen that's around to lay eggs. So again, we can understand
why you'd say the egg is permissible if you don't hold of
מוקצה, muktzah, but why should the mother be permissible? I mean, that's
a, you know, that's a
לגדל ביצים, legadel beitzim, היא ואמה אסורה. hi ve-imma asurah. It and
the mother should be forbidden. Excuse me, I said that wrong because
the egg and the mother are both the מוקצה muktzah problem. But
the point is that we are now working with the assumption that
nobody is arguing on the מוקצה muktzah point, that the whole debate
of בית הלל ובית שמאי Beis Hillel ve-Beis Shammai is about a
hen that is standing around to be eaten. So if it is
a hen that is standing around for laying eggs, how could רבי
אליעזר say it's permissible? It shouldn't be permissible at all, it's מוקצה.
muktzah. So אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, so רב זירא Rav
Zeira said, תאכל אגב אמה, tochal agav immah, you can eat it
through its mother, on the basis of its mother. What does it
mean on the basis of its mother? היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's
the
case? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, כגון שלקחה סתם. kegon she-lekachah stam. Now
of course, you know, this is the case that I was waiting
for somebody to ask me. Until now the whole question has been:
is it set aside for laying eggs or is it set aside
for eating? But say you don't know? You have a lot of
hens around, they lay eggs which you're very happy with, some of
them you're going to want to שחט, shacht, others of them you're
going to want to keep on laying eggs. You just bought it,
you haven't made up your mind. Okay, so what would be the
הלכה halakha there? So he is saying and again, to remind you,
if the hen was set aside for eating it's not מוקצה, muktzah,
the egg is not מוקצה, muktzah, the only possible issue with the
egg is some external question like fruit from a tree, and if
the hen is set aside for making eggs, it's מוקצה muktzah and
the egg is מוקצה. muktzah. So here the scenario is you bought
it without yet identifying what its use would be. כגון שלקחה סתם,
Kegon she-lakcha stam, you purchased it
and you haven't made up your mind yet. So נשחטה, Nishcheta,
if you decide on יום טוב, Yom Tov "Hey, I'm going to
שחט shecht this," then הוברר דלאכילה עומדת, huverar d'la-achilah omedet,
then that retroactively shows that this was a hen that was gonna
be eaten. So and therefore not only can you eat the mother,
you can eat the egg. לא נשחטה, Lo nishcheta,
if you went through יום טוב Yom Tov? not שחט-ing shecht it,
but now you want to know what can I do with the
egg? So you know, "What can I do with the egg? Rabbi,
what can I do with this egg that my hen laid on
יום טוב?" Yom Tov. Well, you know, why bother asking about the
egg? Just שחט shecht the chicken and you'll have chicken for יום
טוב. Yom Tov "No, no, no, I don't want to שחט shecht
the chicken." So why don't you want to שחט shecht the chicken?
So it could be, you know, I don't want to, even if
I want to eat, I don't want to eat it now. But
we're going to say, if you are choosing not to שחט shecht
the chicken, that will interpret it as a hen that is set
aside for laying eggs. So in that case,
לא נשחטה הוברר דלביצים עומדת, lo nishcheta huverar d'l'beitzim omedet, that'll make
it clear that it's around for laying eggs. So this is interesting
because of this extra
word that the egg and its mother, why to mention the mother?
That leads the גמרא Gemara to finally address the case of what
the case of סתם stam when you haven't identified what the purpose
of the hen is. Okay, and there the גמרא Gemara says that
you can use the question of whether you wind up eating the
mother to retroactively identify what the purpose of the hen was and
therefore what the status of the egg was. So that's a principle
of ברירה.
breira. Yeah, yeah, right, exactly.
It's also an interesting question about מוקצה, muktzeh, right? What do you
do if something is essentially ספק מוקצה, safek muktzeh, like if you're
not sure whether you wanted it to be off limits? Right, you
might not even need ברירה, breira, maybe just a ספק מוקצה שרי
safek muktzeh shari because it's not clearly off limits. But anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara deals with it based on what's going to happen
to the mother, yes.
This gets to the question I asked before.
Some breeds of chickens are bred for laying eggs and some for
being.
Yeah, I assume that if it's really an issue of a breed
then that would have the more dominant impact להלכה. l'halacha. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara says, "So that's one answer." What it means is you
don't know what the status of the mother is, you can decide
on יום טוב Yom Tov, and that will then decide the status
of the
egg. רב מרי אמר, Rav Mari amar, גוזמא קתני. guzma katani. Now
גוזמא guzma is not a word in English, it means, I mean,
we normally translate it as an exaggeration. We all know what an
exaggeration is, right? Like, like you know, nobody ever saw שמחת בית
השואבה Simchas Beis HaShoeiva and its like, there
were four hundred gallons of oil, etc. Now the גמרא Gemara actually
treats that as literal, but okay, we know what an exaggeration is.
But the גמרא Gemara here is using גוזמא guzma not as an
exaggeration but as almost like, you know, saying extra things to drive
home your point and for emphasis. And the basic point is you're
right, there's only a חידוש chiddush about the egg, not about the
mother. But if I want to tell you how מותר mutar the
egg is, I'm going to tell you, "The egg? Go ahead, eat
the egg, eat the mother!" So I'm not really, obviously everybody knows
you can eat the mother if the mother's set aside for eating,
but I'm just doing it to strengthen my point. And that's גוזמא,
guzma, like to just talk a lot and to show how, you
know, as a way of underscoring it. So that's גוזמא קתני guzma
katani and this is clearly the easier read of this ברייתא. Braisa,
דתניא, Detanya, we learn a ברייתא, Beraita אחרים אומרים משום רבי אליעזר,
Acherim omrim mishum Rabi Eliezer,
this is exactly the quote we had before, ביצתה תאכל, beitzatah te'achel,
eat the egg, or תאכל, tochal, you should eat it, it can
be eaten, היא, hi, it,
ואמה, v'imah, its mother, ואפרוחה, v'efrochah, and if it has a chick,
eat the chick, וקליפתה, v'klipatah, and go ahead, eat the shell, גזונטהייט,
gezuntaheit, eat everything. Okay, now the only חידוש chiddush there, well maybe
how do you eat shell? But the only חידוש chiddush there is
about the egg. But we say all that stuff to just underscore.
You're not going to forget after today's שיעור shiur that this image
of, "Go ahead, eat the egg, eat the mother, eat the chick."
So that underscores the point. It's not a logical argument but it
emphasizes the point. So the גמרא Gemara says, "Now look, maybe you
want to say no, no, no, we're being very literal." If you're
being literal, what does the word "shell" mean? Eat the shell? מאי
קליפתה, Mai klipatah, why are you saying eat the shell? אילימא קליפה
ממש, Ilima klipah mamash, if literally it means eat the shell, קליפה
בת אכילה היא, klipah bar achilah hi, does anybody eat a shell?
Is it something that can be eaten? אלא אפרוח בקליפתה. Ela efroach
b'klipatah. So what you're going to say is it doesn't mean the
chick and the shell, it means eat the whole chick within its
shell, which is not a bad argument. Yeah, you've laid an egg,
eat the egg, eat the mother, what? There's a live chick in
the egg? Eat the chick with the shell! You know, go ahead,
eat everything! Okay, but if that's true, he says, then that's not
להלכה. l'halacha. Why is it not
להלכה? l'halacha? עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב,
Ad kan lo pligi rabbanan alei d'Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov, so there's
a debate we're going to see very soon between the רבנן rabbanan
and רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov about a chick
before it's opened its eyes. Is that yet a considered an independent
identity or is that אבר מן החי? eiver min ha-chai? It's a
piece of meat that fell off of the mother like the egg
is the fruit that fell off the tree, mother. This is a
and therefore it's a limb from a living animal and you can't
open it. When does it become get its own identity? In the
ישיבה yeshiva dot net last few days we've been learning beginning of
life issues, right, and then that's the abortion question, right? When does
the fetus get its own identity? What degree is it part of
the mother and so on. one way of framing the question. So
here there's a debate. Is it
מותר mutar after the egg has cracked before the chick opens its
eyes, and when does it become its own thing and not part
of the mother? So גמרא Gemara says like this: עד כאן לא
פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Ad kan lo pligi Rabbanan
alei de-Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov,
until now the rabbis didn't argue on רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov, אלא היכא דיצא לאוויר העולם, ela heicha deyatzah l'avir
ha-olam,
once the egg has cracked and the chick has come into the
world, but just not opened its eyes, that's a debate here. אבל
היכא דלא יצא לאוויר העולם, aval heicha delo yatza l'avir ha-olam, while
it's still in the egg, לא פליגי, lo pligi, they don't debate,
everybody says it's forbidden. Okay? It's all, so therefore since the
what does this statement mean eat the chicken and eat the shell?
If it's literal then nobody eats the shell. If it means eat
the chick while it's in the shell, that's אסור. assur. Forget about
יום טוב, Yom Tov it's אסור assur because it's still a part
of the mother because it's like it's like אבר מן החי. eiver
min ha-chai. So what does it mean? אלא אפרוח וקליפתו גוזמא ela
efroach u-kliptato guzma would be we're being exaggerating, we're just being there's
got to be a better word for that in English in this
case, not
what's that word embellishing. We're talking in an embellished way. So therefore,
yeah, eat the chick, eat the shell. So הכא נמי hacha nami
תאכל היא ואמה, tochal hi v'imah,
eat it, eat its mother. גוזמא, guzma, we're just embellishing. Okay? So
anyway the point is don't get worked up about the phrase that
was a way of underscoring but what's fascinating here is it's not
just בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Here we have a position that even
when the hen is set aside for eating and therefore it's obvious
you can eat the hen because it's set aside for eating, we
have a position that rejects this idea of בית הלל Beit Hillel
that the egg is a problem. We have a tradition not only
of בית שמאי Beit Shammai but of רבי אליעזר who said. Now
רבי אליעזר was בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, I don't know if few
people know that. So it's not so much of a separate tradition.
But anyway it's interesting to be quoted of רבי אליעזר the same
thing that the egg is forbidden even when the mother is set
aside for eating even though obviously the mother is I'm sorry I
keep on saying forbidden
I'm not well I woke up a little sick today. Anyway, so
we have this tradition of בית שמאי Beit Shammai that the egg
is permissible when the mother is set aside for eating and that's
what this ברייתא Baraisa, is saying the same way you can eat
the mother you can eat the egg no problem the position of
בית שמאי Beit Shammai that the egg is permissible. Okay now the
גמרא Gemara goes
on. איתמר itmar was taught. שבת ויום טוב, Shabbat v'Yom Tov, let's
say you have שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov back to
back. Okay for them it was a two day יום טוב Yom
Tov we have three day יום טובס. Yom Tovs. So you have
שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov. back to back. רב אמר
Rav amar נולדה בזה אסורה בזה, nolda be-zeh assurah be-zeh, if it
was born on שבת Shabbat it's going to remain forbidden on יום
טוב. Yom Tov רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar no, נולדה בזה
מותרת בזה. nolda be-zeh muteret be-zeh. No, if it's born on שבת
Shabbat by יום טוב Yom Tov it'll be permissible or the reverse
it was born on יום טוב Yom Tov if the juxtaposition was
it'll become permissible on שבת. Shabbat. So what's that a debate about?
So the גמרא Gemara says here's what it's about. נימא קסבר רב
קדושה אחת היא. neima kasavar Rav kedusha achat hi. So the most
logical debate is when יום טוב Yom Tov and שבת Shabbat come
juxtaposed do you look at it as a continuous single קדושה kedusha
or do you look at it as two separate קדושות. kedushot. Now
obvious way to tell is that when what do we do when
יום טוב Yom Tov precedes שבת? Shabbat? I mean follows שבת. Shabbat.
What do we do at when we're bringing in יום טוב Yom
Tov if יום טוב Yom Tov follows שבת? Shabbat? We make הבדלה.
havdala. So clearly indicates the idea that we don't see it as
a continuous. Indeed it's the most discontinuous. It's not like two days
יום טוב Yom Tov or two days ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Here
שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov has very different characters and
halakhic statuses and so on. But the גמרא Gemara is saying maybe
there is that opinion that it's all one continuous thing so if
it's born on one of the two days it remains forbidden on
both. Okay and that would be the logic and it's permissible because
you see it as two separate entities. So the גמרא Gemara says
you can't say that because that would have רב Rav saying that
it's one קדושה. kedusha. והאמר רב, v'ha'amar Rav, רב Rav says in
another context הלכה כארבעה זקנים, halakha k'arba'a zekenim, we follow the four
elders ואליבא דרבי אליעזר v'aliba de-Rabbi Eliezer and who go according to
רבי אליעזר דאמר d'amar who says שתי קדושות הן, shtei kedushot hen,
it's two קדושות. kedushot. So we don't worry whatever this four elders
is but the point is רב Rav says it's שתי קדושות. shtei
kedushot. So if רב Rav
says שבת ויום טוב Shabbat v'Yom Tov is שתי קדושות shtei kedushot
why when it's born on one is it forbidden on the other?
Right? If שבת—let's Shabbat say it was born on יום טוב Yom
Tov. and now שבת Shabbat is coming in. So now I don't
ask the same מוקצה muktza question from yesterday I ask the שבת
Shabbat question by itself. It's about to be שבת. Shabbat. What's מוקצה
muktza what's not מוקצה? muktza? Anything that already existed in the world
and I had a reasonable opportunity to use is not going to
be מוקצה muktza now that שבת Shabbat is coming in even though
it was born on יום טוב. Yom Tov יום טוב Yom Tov
is just the day before שבת Shabbat and it was an egg
that was in the world before שבת Shabbat began and if each
day is distinct I'll say as שבת Shabbat begins this is something
that's already exists and that I can eat. So then what would
be the logic that you can't eat it? So the גמרא Gemara
says why would רב Rav say you can't eat it? אלא ela
says the גמרא Gemara הכא בהכנה דרבה קמיפלגי. hacha be-hachana d'Rabbah kamiflegi.
The issue is again that famous הכנה hachana that רבה Rabbah introduced
which is you'll remember a classic case of that is יום טוב
Yom Tov? and שבת Shabbat juxtaposed. And רבה'ס Rabbah's idea is not
just מוקצה muktza did it exist but was it something that was
prepared on the weekday for the sake of שבת Shabbat and יום
טוב? Yom Tov, And this egg... was only prepared, finished in the
mother on יום טוב, Yom Tov. and then שבת Shabbos came along.
So רב Rav אית ליה הכנה דרבה. is lei hachana de-Rabbah. רב
Rav has רבה Rabbah's problem, so the egg has to be finished
while it's still weekday, even if it's שתי קדושות. shtei kedushot. רבי
יוחנן לית ליה הכנה דרבה, Rebbi Yochanan leis lei hachana de-Rabbah, and
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan does not hold of that concern. And therefore,
since it was around yesterday, when שבת Shabbos comes, that's enough, even
if it wasn't finished on a חול chol day. כתנאי, Kitannai, this
is like the following debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. נולדה בשבת תאכל ביום טוב, Nolada be-Shabbos tochal be-Yom Tov,
if it
was born on שבת, Shabbos, eat it the following day, which is
יום טוב. Yom Tov, ביום טוב תאכל בשבת, Be-Yom Tov tochal be-Shabbos,
it was born on יום טוב, Yom Tov. eat it on שבת,
Shabbos, even if it's the following day.
I assume they mean it raw.
Yeah, exactly. רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי אליעזר עדיין היא מחלוקת. Rabbi
Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer adayin hi machlokes. No, that debate of
בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel applies even in
this case, שבית שמאי אומרים תאכל ובית הלל אומרים לא תאכל. she-Beis
Shammai omrim tochal u-Beis Hillel omrim lo tochal. The בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says
eat it and בית הלל Beis Hillel says do not eat it.
So even though it was born yesterday, you can't eat it. Why
would that be? If they are שתי קדושות? shtei kedushot? So the
גמרא Gemara says, ah, this is the debate, and this exactly is
the debate of רב Rav and רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. And the
reason is not חדא קדושה, chada kedusha, the reason is this idea
of הכנה דרבה, hachana de-Rabbah, which required it to be ready from
a weekday. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, it
ends with some story. Yeah, but can't you
cook it on שבת?
Shabbos? No, on יום טוב.
Yom Tov No, but he's describing a scenario where it was born
on יום טוב Yom Tov, and then
הלילה ha-layla on יום טוב, Yom Tov right? And you can eat
it on שבת. Shabbos. The only opportunity you have to eat it
raw.
I thought we were talking about when it's...
we're talking about both scenarios.
So שבת Shabbos scenario, eat it raw. אושפיזכניה דרב דרב אדא בר
אהבה,
Ushpizchaneih de-Rav
de-Rav Adda bar
Ahava,
so
the host, the proprietor of his inn or wherever he was staying,
of the landlord of his building, הוו ליה
הנך ביצים. havu lei hanach beitzim. He had some eggs מיום טוב
לשבת. mi-Yom Tov le-Shabbos. They were born on יום טוב Yom Tov
and he wanted to know if he could eat them on שבת.
Shabbos. So אתא לקמיה, ata lekamei, he came to him. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava said
to him, מה רבותא הוא האידנא ונכלינהו למחר? mah rvat bona hu
idna ve-nichlinhu le-machar? Now you want to eat it tomorrow on שבת,
Shabbos, but who wants to eat raw eggs? Can I fry up
some eggs, scramble up some eggs, and I'll eat them today on
יום טוב Yom Tov and eat them tomorrow on שבת? Shabbos? So
it's a classic question of can you prepare on יום טוב Yom
Tov, for שבת, Shabbos, עירוב תבשילין, Eruv Tavshilin, etc. That was the
question he had, can I cook this? It never occurred to him
to think that the egg might be מוקצה. muktzah. He never read
the first משנה Mishna of our מסכת. masechet. So he said, אמר
ליה, amar lei, so רב Rav said back to him, מאי דעתך?
mai daitach? What is your assuming? In terms of thinking that you
can, if it's born today, you can use it tomorrow. So besides
the question of am I allowed to cook today for the sake
of tomorrow, but your assumption you could use it tomorrow? רב ורבי
יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוחנן. Rav u-Rebbi Yochanan halacha ke-Rebbi Yochanan. First of
all, we rule like רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, which is... and I'm
sorry, and רב ורבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוחנן. Rav u-Rebbi Yochanan halacha
ke-Rebbi Yochanan. And you want me to say that this is the
debate of רב Rav and רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, and we should
rule in general like רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, and therefore according to
רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, if it's born yesterday on יום טוב, Yom
Tov it's מותר mutter on שבת. Shabbos. But one minute, אפילו רבי
יוחנן לא קשרי אלא לגומעו, afillu Rebbi Yochanan lo kashrei ella le-gomao,
exactly as you were asking. Even רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says if
it was born on יום טוב Yom Tov. it's permissible on שבת,
Shabbos, that's to swallow it raw, לגומעו למחר. le-gomao le-machar. אבל ביומיה
לא, Aval be-yomei lo, but you can't handle it today on יום
טוב. Yom Tov, Okay? So forget about cooking. Today it's מוקצה, muktzah,
tomorrow it'll be permissible. So even as today's יום טוב, Yom Tov,
tomorrow's שבת, Shabbos, you can't say, can I cook with it for
tomorrow? Today it's מוקצה. muktzah. It becomes a problem tomorrow. Okay, so
that though is interesting, but we do rule like רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan that when it comes tomorrow, you're allowed to eat it. So
now the גמרא says like this,
והתניא, ve-hatanya, and we taught in a ברייתא, Braita. this is not
a question, it's a support. אחד ביצה שנולדה בשבת ואחד ביצה שנולדה
ביום טוב, Achad beitzi she-nolada be-Shabbos ve-achad beitzi she-nolada be-Yom Tov, whether
it was born on שבת Shabbos or on יום טוב, Yom Tov.
אין מטלטלין אותה. ein mtaltelin osah. And here's an explicit discussion of
it as מוקצה, muktzah, you can't move it. This is exactly what
we quoted before. לא לכסות בה את הכלי ולא לסמוך בה כרעי
המיטה, Lo lechasos bah es ha-kli ve-lo lismoch bah karai ha-mita, not
to use as a bowl-stopper, not to use it for your bed,
however you're supporting your bed with it. And therefore, even if it's
מותר mutter tomorrow, but today it's אסור, assur, like בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. אושפיזכניה דרב פפא, Ushpizchaneih de-Rav Pappa, so there
was now another story, the proprietor of רב פפא'ס Rav Pappa's establishment,
ואמרי לה ההוא גברא, ve-amrei lah hahu gavra, and some say just
some random guy,
דאתא לקמיה דרב פפא, de-asa lekamei de-Rav Pappa, it doesn't really matter
who the guy was, he came to רב Rav פפא. הוו ליה
הנך ביצים משבת ליום טוב, Havu lei hanach beitzim mi-Shabbos le-Yom Tov,
he has the reverse case, an egg that was born on שבת,
Shabbos, and he wanted to know can I eat it tomorrow which
is יום טוב. Yom Tov. Again, the question of רב Rav and
רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. אתא לקמיה, Ata lekamei, he came to him.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, מהו למיכלינהו למחר, mahu le-michlinhu le-machar, can I
eat it tomorrow? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, so he didn't give him
a straight answer. זיל, Zil, he said, go האידנא, idna, leave me
today, תא למחר, sa le-machar, come back tomorrow. I'll tell you tomorrow.
Why?
דרב, De-Rav, one minute, oh he will tell him when he comes
back tomorrow, assuming he comes back. דרב לא מוקי אמורא עליה מיומא
טבא לחבריה. de-Rav lo moki amora alei mi-yoma tava le-chavrei. רב Rav
would not appoint an אמורא, amora, the אמורא amora like we use
the word תנא tanna and אמורא amora to mean like רבינא Ravina
or רב אשי, Rav Ashi, you know, בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, but the I call those. capital T תנא, Tanna,
capital A אמורא. Amora. There was also a lowercase t תנא, Tanna,
lowercase a אמורא. Amora. So the תנא Tanna in the time of
the משנה Mishna was the person that memorized all of the oral
sayings, all of the oral tradition and all the sayings that became
the משנה and the ברייתא. Braita משנה and ברייתא also were taught
as a memorized book, not as a literal written book. But anyway,
the תנא Tanna there was the one who was the בר אורין
bar orian of the day, the storehouse of all of the sayings
and the knowledge. An אמורא Amora was different. An אמורא, Amora, because
what do אמוראים Amoraim do? אמוראים Amoraim just give their pieces of
information, and תנאים, Tannaim, they give their pieces of information. אמוראים Amoraim
argue, they discuss. So an אמורא, Amora, I mean by parallel, is
somebody that actually is not just saying over from collected knowledge, but
is my basically loudspeaker. If I'm the אמורא, Amora, if I'm רבי
מאיר, then I bring Charlie and I can't yell to this audience
of a thousand people, I chose Charlie because he's got a good
voice, and I just say to Charlie, okay, tell them in this
case, da da da, this is a הלכה, halacha, and then he
yells it out to everyone. So he's my אמורא. Amora. So that's
the other use of the word אמורא. Amora. Okay, so רב Rav
would not have an אמורא Amora stand by him when at the,
רש"י Rashi explains it like the first night of יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Okay, because basically he wouldn't give a שיעור, shiur, and in
the middle of the שיעור shiur he would often give פסק הלכה,
psak halacha, he refused to do it at the night of יום
טוב. Yom Tov Why? משום שכרות, mishum shichrus,
because he would be drunk. Wow. So he would drink a lot,
have a lot of wine at the meal, so he would not
go ahead and give a שיעור. shiur. So this guy came to
him, יום טוב Yom Tov, night, after he had a lot of
wine, and as we're going to, and as
we read in the תורה Torah that we read recently, the role
of the כהנים Kohanim is also that to פסקן, pasken, and you
can't פסקן pasken when you're drunk, and therefore, and he knew that
if he gave a שיעור shiur on any topic, he'd wind up
throwing up some פסק הלכה, psak halacha, couldn't help himself. So therefore
רב Rav would not give a שיעור shiur and he certainly wouldn't
answer halachic שאלות. shaylas. So he told him to come back tomorrow.
כי אתא למחר, ki asa lemachar, guess what, he actually did come
back tomorrow. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, here's the
הלכה. halacha. Remember it was יום טוב, Yom Tov the egg was
laid on יום טוב Yom Tov and he wanted to know, 'Can
I use it on שבת?' Shabbos? איסרו השתא אסתלעי, isru hashta istalai,
and you know what, it's good that I didn't פסקן pasken for
you yesterday. The first thing he said is, 'Have I had I,
had it been otherwise, had I answered you yesterday, אסתלעי istalai I
would have made an error.' דאמר לך, da'amar lach, what would I
have told you? I would have said רב רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי
יוחנן. Rav Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke-Rabbi Yochanan. We rule like רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, if it's born on
יום טוב Yom Tov you can use it on שבת. Shabbos. That
would have been the first thing that popped into my head if
you asked me yesterday when I wasn't thinking straight, I'd tell you
fine, it's permissible. But I'm not going to tell you that anymore.
Aren't you glad we waited? אמר רבא, amar Rava, רבא Rava says,
הלכתא כוותיה דרב בהני תלתא. hilchata kevasei de-Rav behani telasa.
We rule like רב Rav in these three things. We don't have
to worry about the three things, but one of them is our
case of שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov with the egg.
בין לקולא בין לחומרא. bein lekula bein lechumra. Whether רב Rav is
being more lenient or being מחמיר, machmir, in three areas we rule
like him when a debate of רב Rav and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and one of them is the egg. So here you actually
have not only a debate of רב Rav and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, it's a debate of תנאים Tannaim and it's a debate of
the אמוראים Amoraim who to פסקן pasken like. Okay, so let's just
take a moment, what are the things we've introduced so far because
it's been a lot of ideas. One idea is that the idea
of דבר שיש לו מתירין not only applies to תערובת, ta'aroves, but
even applies to ספק ספיקא safeik safeika and ספק דרבנן. safeik d'rabbanan.
That was fascinating. Back to the egg, what did we learn? We
had a tradition of רבי אליעזר who said like בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai, רבי אליעזר מבית שמאי, Rabbi Eliezer mi-Beis Shammai, that you can't
eat the egg, assuming again the hen was set aside for eating,
but then he uses very flowery language or whatever extreme language, eat
the egg, eat the mother, eat the chick, etc. And now we're
introducing the question, if it's born on שבת Shabbos is it permissible
on יום טוב Yom Tov or vice-versa? In order to say that
you have to say it's two קדושות, kedushos, which we obviously do
because we make הבדלה, havdalah, but even if you say it's two
קדושות, kedushos, the question is, is the position of הכנה דרבה? hachana
de-Rabbah? And that's a debate of רב and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
whether we're worried about הכנה דרבה hachana de-Rabbah or not. Okay, now
the גמרא continues. אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan and now we
get to another case, taking us away from the egg a little
bit but still in the land of מוקצה. muktza. So let's take
a look. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, עצים שנשרו מן הדקל
בשבת. etzim shenashru min ha-dekel b'Shabbos. עץ, etz, wood fell off of
a tree on שבת, Shabbos, a branch fell
down. אסור להסיקם ביום טוב. assur le-hatzikam be-Yom Tov. And again it's
a שבת Shabbos יום טוב Yom Tov, case. So it fell down
on שבת, Shabbos, tomorrow's יום טוב, Yom Tov? can I use the
branch that fell down yesterday on שבת Shabbos in order to put
into my fire for my firewood? And he says you
can't. אל תשיבני ביצה. al tachshiveini beitza. Don't tell me, 'Ah, but
ביצה beitza you're allowed to do it.' So why is שבת Shabbos
to any different? מאי טעמא ביצה, mai ta'ama beitza, why by ביצה
beitza you're allowed to do it? משום, mishum, where am I? דביומא
נמי חזיא לגומעא, debiyoma nami chazya l'gum'a, because on שבת Shabbos itself,
if an egg was born on שבת, Shabbos, why could you use
it the next day on יום טוב? Yom Tov, Because on שבת
Shabbos itself it was raw and it was possible to be used.
So therefore, and the only reason it was forbidden and the only
reason you didn't use it was because of this idea of מוקצה.
muktza. So מוקצה muktza on שבת Shabbos and then following is יום
טוב, Yom Tov יום טוב Yom Tov. is its own
day. אפילו גומע, afilu gome'a,
because he could swallow it. I'm sorry today. Where am
I? Okay. משום דביומא נמי חזי לגומא, mishum d'veyoma nami chazi l'goma,
ולא קשרי ליה אלא למחר, v'lo kashrei lei ela l'machar, so and
if we're not going to permit you to eat it, we're not,
we're not going to permit you to eat it until tomorrow, it
was born today on שבת Shabbos we say eat it tomorrow, you'll
never anyway eat it on שבת Shabbos because you know because it
is.
I'm sorry. Alright, so here's the story.
The egg is born on שבת Shabbos so you're going to פסקן
paskin like like רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, it can be eaten on
the following day that's יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's not a מוקצה
Muktzeh concern, שתי קדושות, shetei kedushot, it was ready yesterday, you can
eat it on יום טוב. Yom Tov, Okay, but in the exact
same scenario he's saying by a tree branch that fell down you
can't. Why? He's saying look, here's the difference. The egg, if we,
when we're telling you it's אסור assur on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
don't use it today use it tomorrow, you know that there's only
one reason you're not using this egg that was laid today, which
is what? מוקצה. Muktzeh. But by the trees, if the branch, if
we tell you don't use it today use it tomorrow, there's a
different reason why you're not using the branch right on שבת Shabbos
which is
you can't do
anything with it right and it's מוקצה. Muktzeh. Okay, so therefore here's
going to be the issue. So let's take a look.
Here's שבת, Shabbos, here's יום טוב, Yom Tov okay. In the case
that the egg was born here, right, so if it weren't for
מוקצה Muktzeh you would use it, you would swallow it. But we
say don't swallow it because of מוקצה. Muktzeh. Okay, and then you
can use it though tomorrow. So that's not going to be a
problem. You're going to understand that מוקצה Muktzeh applies to eggs that
are laid, I didn't use it yesterday, I could've used it, I
could've had it raw but I didn't use it yesterday, so it
doesn't, it applies to eggs that are laid but I'm allowed to
use it tomorrow because you know because they're שתי קדושות. shetei kedushot.
But if you've got your branch of your tree that fell down
here, right, and you're not going to use it on שבת, Shabbos,
are you going to know that the reason you're not using it
is because of the idea of מוקצה? Muktzeh? Maybe there's another reason.
Right, what legitimate purpose can you put you know can you put
that branch to on שבת? Shabbos? So when you come to use
it on יום טוב Yom Tov, you won't realize that fundamentally the
principle of מוקצה Muktzeh applies. Let's read that. Okay. So in that
case since it was you could've had it raw, ולא קשרי ליה
אלא למחר v'lo kashrei lei ela l'machar and we're going to say
don't eat it today on שבת Shabbos eat it tomorrow on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, מדיומא דבת יומא אסורה mideyoma d'vas yoma asura that'll
be a very clear message. Why did I eat that egg yesterday?
Oh yeah I wasn't allowed to eat it because it was born
on yesterday. That'll be what you understand. So just because we're allowing
you to do it on on יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's not
going to lead to you to then assume that there's no problem
with the egg and you could eat it even on even when
the day it was laid. But אצן דלאו חזי ליומיה, atzan d'lav
chazi l'yomei, but wood that falls from a tree that you had
nothing to use it for on שבת, Shabbos, so אי שרי ליה
למחר ei sharei lei l'machar if we'll say use the wood tomorrow
on יום טוב, Yom Tov אתי למימר ati l'meimar you will come
and say, oh look, a tree branch that fell down isn't מוקצה,
Muktzeh, they let me use it on יום טוב Yom Tov, so
why didn't I use it on שבת? Shabbos? דיומא נמי שרי d'yoma
nami sharei really on its own day it would be permissible, I
didn't use it on שבת Shabbos because you can't, what was I
going to do with a branch on שבת? Shabbos? But maybe they'll
say that the fact that you're letting me use it tomorrow proves
that it's really is not fundamentally a problem of מוקצה. Muktzeh. דהא
משום שבת הוא דלא חזי לאסקוני d'ha mishum shabbos hu d'lo chazi
l'askunei it was just yesterday that I couldn't burn it on שבת.
Shabbos. Alright, so is that clear? The basic principle is שתי קדושות,
shetei kedushot, נולד בזה מותר בזה, nolad b'zeh mutar b'zeh, but now
we're introducing a new concern. If an egg that was laid, even
if halachically it's שתי קדושות, shetei kedushot, like let's even call it
a three-day יום טוב, Yom Tov, not three-day יום טוב, Yom Tov.
two days and שבת. Shabbos. But even so halachically it's שתי קדושות,
shetei kedushot, not necessarily experientially. So if we tell you don't eat
the egg today eat it tomorrow, you will never think oh there's
no problem of an egg that was laid because they're letting me
eat it because you'll say no I couldn't have eaten it yesterday,
so fundamentally there is a problem and you'll understand why we're letting
you do it on יום טוב. Yom Tov But if we say
the same by the law of wood, go ahead and and use
it tomorrow, so you're going to say look tomorrow, today, fundamentally a
log that falls from the tree or branch falls from a tree
is not a problem, only reason I didn't use it yesterday was
because what was I going to do with it yesterday? And therefore
you will experientially think of this as one קדושה kedusha and infer
from the fact that we're letting you use it on יום טוב
Yom Tov that in principle you could use it on שבת. Shabbos.
And therefore you're going to come to assume that things that are
born you know and fall off of trees and whatever are fundamentally
not a problem. Yes.
By this logic רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan would probably say that if
a branch falls off a tree on a first day יום טוב
Yom Tov. it ought to be able to be burnt on the
second day יום טוב.
yom tov Yeah, if we say שתי קדושות shetei kedushot by that,
which we do. But yeah. Okay, so it goes like this. אמר
רב מתנא. Amar Rav Masna. So now we've introduced the idea of
two days, שתי קדושות, shetei kedushot, נולד בזה מותר בזה nolad b'zeh
mutar b'zeh or not. We basically פסקן paskin it is מותר בזה,
mutar b'zeh, it's שתי קדושות, shetei kedushot, but then the question is
will it sometimes lead to the old slippery slope and there might
be cases where we don't want you to use it yesterday because
then you'll make wrong inferences about the day before. Now, אמר רב
מתנא, Amar Rav Masna, said רב מתנא, Rav Masna, עצים שנשרו מן
הדקל לתוך התנור, etzim shenashru min hadekel letoch hatanur, while we're talking
about wood. trees and branches that fall from the tree and the
מוקצה *muktzah* problem on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because of something new,
let's say it was an overhanging of your oven and it fell
straight into your oven. So what, what do I do now? Like
do I stick my hand in the oven, stay with it out?
So, in that case, ביום טוב *beYom Tov* what do you do?
מרבה להם עצים מוכנים ומסיקן *marbe lahem etzim muchanim umasiken*. Just throw
in extra wood and make it a רוב *rov* and make it
בטל *battel* and go ahead and use it. Okay? So the גמרא
*Gemara* says והא כמהפך באיסורא *veha kamapeich be'issura*. Now one minute, it
assumed that the idea of throwing in extra wood means that when
I stir it, which is something they would normally do, that you're
only stirring the כשר *kosher* wood, not the you know the non-מוקצה
*muktzah* wood. The גמרא *Gemara* says that's not true. You're going to
be stirring the non-מוקצה *muktzah* wood the מוקצה *muktzah* wood as well,
all the wood will be stirred and you're moving מוקצה *muktzah*. By
the way, it's fundamentally not a problem to use מוקצה *muktzah*, the
fundamental problem is to and the רשב"א *Rashba* comments on this on
the גמרא *Gemara*, the גמרא *Gemara*'s problem was only about stirring it,
not about it being burnt. The fundamental problem is not about using
מוקצה *muktzah*, it's moving מוקצה *muktzah*. When I was growing up, right
we thought מוקצה *muktzah* was the cooties. So if you don't touch
a car, it's מוקצה *muktzah*, right? Not only is it not allowed
to touch a car, in principle you can sit on a car
because you're not moving it. You can sit on a rock. Okay?
Now am I a little bit moving it? It goes down a
little bit. Am I really moving it from its place? It's only
part of the fence. So you're basically allowed to use מוקצה *muktzah*,
you just can't move מוקצה *muktzah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, I
don't understand, it's wonderful you added more wood, you're still going to
stir it, you're still going to move the מוקצה *muktzah*. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this: No, כיון דרובא היתירא *keivan deruba heteira*,
since now the majority of it is permissible wood, so כיון דרובא
היתירא נינהו כי קמהפך בהתירא קמהפך *keivan deruba heteira ninhu ki kamapeich
beheteira kamapeich*, you're just, you're just, let's say you're just stirring the
majority of the wood and you are not and you are not
stirring the actual the מוקצה *muktzah* wood itself, which means basically we
put in a majority and we make it בטל *battel*. So this
is a fascinating idea like we know you can do ביטול *bittul*
by food, whoever heard you do ביטול *bittul* by מוקצה *muktzah*? But
again, most מוקצה *muktzah* is distinct and you know where it is
and you can't say ביטול *bittul*, but you throw a lot of
logs of wood together, it's not clear which is the logs and
whatever, and therefore you can apply the principle of ביטול *bittul*. One
minute, so the גמרא *Gemara* says והא כמבטל איסור לכתחילה *veha kamvattel
issur l'chatchila*?
One minute, but you are willingly creating ביטול *bittul*. We can't do
that. I can't just go ahead and take a little חזיר *chazir*,
you know sauce and put it in my soup and say, oh,
ביטול *bittul*! You know? You're not allowed to. ביטול *bittul* is for
post-facto situations, you can't say it לכתחילה *l'chatchila*. דתנן אין מבטלין איסור
לכתחילה *detnan ein mevatlin issur l'chatchila*. We have a משנה *mishna* that
says you do not, you do not cause ביטול *bittul* of a
forbidden thing at the outset, you only deal with it once it's
already happened. The גמרא *Gemara* says, no, הני מילי דאורייתא *hani mili
d'Oraisa*. That's when it's a biblical problem, like חזיר *chazir*, meat in
milk, then we don't do ביטול *bittul* from the outset. אבל בדרבנן
*aval beRabbanan*, but if it's only a rabbinic issue, מבטלינן *mevatlinan*, we
can actually actively do ביטול *bittul*. Now this גמרא *Gemara* says it
as a big categorical comment. If so, wow, כשרות *kashrut* would be
so much easier, you know, we could actively do ביטול *bittul* on
rabbinic problems, so much of plus a large percentage of כשרות *kashrut*
problems are rabbinic. But basically there's a lot of evidence in other
גמרות *Gemaras* that that's not true, that you cannot, you cannot proactively
do ביטול *bittul* even by דרבנן *deRabbanan*. So they basically say this
is a weak דרבנן *deRabbanan*, you know, מוקצה *muktzah* is very different
than other דרבנן *deRabbanan*, and therefore and also as we're going to
see in a minute, it's about to be burnt up, it doesn't
really have so much status and identity. So there's a whole discussion
about this, but don't be misled by this statement. The statement does
sound like you can do ביטול לכתחילה *bittul l'chatchila*, proactive ביטול *bittul*
by דרבנן *deRabbanan*, but what it really means is at least by
this דרבנן *deRabbanan* you can. It's only a דרבנן *deRabbanan*, at least
by this דרבנן *deRabbanan* you can. אבל בדרבנן מבטלינן *aval beRabbanan mevatlinan*
and that's why you throw in extra wood. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, ורב אשי דאמר כל דבר שיש לו מתירין אפילו בדרבנן לא
בטיל *veRav Ashi d'amar kol davar sheyesh lo matirin afilu beRabbanan lo
batil*, מאי איכא למימר *mai ika l'meimar*? Remember we started the day
by רב אשי *Rav Ashi* quoting this whole משנה *mishna* about the
pressed figs and telling us that there's a position, I'm sorry, not
the pressed figs, but the issue about the egg, excuse me. Remember
רב אשי *Rav Ashi* said the egg was the one that was,
we're dealing with? That's why it's not בטל *battel* here, and that's
why, why is the ספק *safek* about the egg about שבת *Shabbat*
and יום טוב *Yom Tov* אסור *assur*? Because even though it's rabbinic,
it's a דבר שיש לו מתירין *davar sheyesh lo matirin*. So now
the גמרא *Gemara* is saying, if that's true, that even rabbinic matters
like the egg is a דבר שיש לו מתירין *davar sheyesh lo
matirin* and we're not even going to rely on ספק *safek*, then
why do we rely on the ביטול *bittul*? You're still being מבטלו
*mevatlo*, right? If the issue here of נתערב באלף כולן אסורות *nitarav
b'elef kullan assurot* is because דבר שיש לו מתירין *davar sheyesh lo
matirin* is not בטל *battel*, so that's exactly the story with the
wood. How can you tell me what we're doing is ביטול *bittul*?
Didn't we learn that ביטול *bittul* doesn't work by דבר שיש לו
מתירין *davar sheyesh lo matirin*? So let's take a look. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, ורב אשי דאמר כל דבר שיש לו מתירין אפילו
בדרבנן לא בטיל *veRav Ashi d'amar kol davar sheyesh lo matirin afilu
beRabbanan lo batil*, מאי איכא למימר *mai ika l'meimar*? How can you
explain it? So how does ביטול *bittul* work? הני מילי היכא דאיתיה
לאיסורא בעיניה *hani mili heicha d'ise l'issura be'eina*. That's when the איסור
*issur* still, you know, really around in its own form. הכא מיקלא
קלי איסורא *hacha mikla kali issura*, here the איסור *issur*'s in the
process of being burned, so again it's just a branch, it's the
branch
to say דבר שיש לו מתירין *davar sheyesh lo matirin* doesn't really
you know doesn't really work, okay, and therefore maybe you could say
it's a specific aspect about the הלכה *halacha* of דבר שיש לו
מתירין *davar sheyesh lo matirin* because it's not like you use it
to... How can I use it tomorrow? It's being burnt right now,
right? So, but
basically whether you, we don't, so even though this has a דבר
שיש לו מתירים quality, we will still allow ביטול to work because
it is in the process of being burnt. Let's read one more
point. איתמר itmar was taught, שני ימים טובים של גלויות, shnei yamim
tovim shel galuyos, let's say you have a two day יום טוב
in חוץ לארץ. chutz laaretz. So רבא אמר, Rava amar, Rava says,
נולד בזה, nolad baze, you know what, let's stop here because it
is already 8:30 and this is already a new topic.